So as we saw in the
cube, we have one cell
in the cube for each combination of
store ID, item ID, and customer ID.
So if those three together form a key, then it's very straight forward.
If the dimension attributes together
don't form a key then
we might be pre-aggregating already inside the data cube.
So, we might decide to already
have say the sum of quantity
times price for each combination
of store item and customer.
Another possibility and it's done
quite commonly is to add
to the fact table the attribute
date, or even the time.
And that can be used to create a key.
Typically, we won't have two
transactions at exactly the same time.
Now if we do have an
attribute here called date, one
might wonder is that a
dimension attribute or a dependent attribute.
Actually, it's pretty much
a dimension attribute because we're
gonna use it as another dimension
in our data cube, but the
difference being that we would
not have an actual dimension table listing the dates.
Now let's move on to
a couple other concepts in the
OLAP world called drill down and roll up.
The idea of drill
down, is that we may
be examining summary data and then we want to get more information.
Drill down into the details of that data.
And, actually, we can think
of that very specifically in
a SQL context as follows.
Let's suppose that we have
this query in SQL which
follows by the way the
description of the query I
had earlier where we'll do a
join and then a selection
and then it grouped by, and finally we have an aggregation here.
So this query specifically is
looking at our total sales broken
out by state and brand.
Maybe we'll look at that and we'll just say that's not enough detail.
I need more information.
So, to drill down what we
do is add a grouping attribute.
So if we added, for example,
category, when we add
another grouping attribute, that gets
us more data in the answer - more detail in our data.
Rollup is exactly the opposite.
Rollup says we're looking at
data and we decide we
have too much detail and we want to summarize.
And summarize is simply
a matter of removing a group by attributes.
So if we took out state, then
now we'll only see our
data summarized by brand
rather than broken out into state and brand.
And lastly, I want to introduce some SQL constructs.
These are constructs that have been added,
fairly recently, to the SQL
standard in order to perform OLAP queries.
And we'll be seeing these in our demo.
The constructs are called with cube
and with roll up and
they're added to the group by clause.
When we add with cube to
a query with a group by
what happens is that, basically,
we're adding to the result
of our query, the faces,
edges, and corner of the cube.
Using no values for the attributes that we're not constraining.
We'll see this clearly in the demo.
With Rollup is similar to With Cube, except it's smaller.
It actually is a portion of
the data cube, and that
makes sense when we have dimensions
that are inherently hierarchical.
And again we'll see that in the demo as well.
So, we can conclude there are
two broad types of data
base activity, online transaction processing.
Short, simple transactions touching
small portions of the data,
lots of updating and OLAP,
or online analytical processing, where
we have complex queries, long transactions,
might touch a large portion of
the data and might not update the data at all.
For online analytical processing OLAP
we saw that star schemas are frequently used.
We saw how to view the data as a data cube.
Of course, that can be in any number of dimensions.
We just use three for visualization.
There are two new
constructs in SQL: With Cube and With Rollup.
And finally this type of
query can be very stressful on
a database system when we have very large databases.
So special techniques have been
introduced into systems to help perform these queries efficiently.