In this video we&#39;ll be doing a live demonstration of OLAP.
We&#39;ll create a star schema similar
to the one we used in our previous examples.
It will be sales data with
a fact table and several
dimension tables and then we&#39;ll
do several different types of OLAP queries.
We&#39;ll show a full star-join over the star schema.
We&#39;ll show some examples of drill-down and roll-up.
We&#39;ll also show what&#39;s known as
slicing and dicing which we
haven&#39;t explained yet, we&#39;ll just do when we get to those queries.
And finally we&#39;ll show the With
Cube and With Rollup
clauses that have been added
to the SQL standard for OLAP queries.
For those we&#39;ll be using
MySQL, actually for the whole demo we&#39;ll be using MySQL.
MySQL supports With Rollup.
Neither of the other systems
that we&#39;ve been using, SQLite
or Postgres supports With Rollup yet.
And MySQL does not yet
support With Cube, but we&#39;ll
see that we can simulate the
behavior With Cube, using
With Rollup command of MySQL.
So let&#39;s move to the demo.
Here we are in the demo, we
have a fact table that
contains information about stores, items and customers.
We don&#39;t see much here except their ID values.
And we have sixty tuples
loaded up in our fact table.
Our dimension tables are the customer table.
We have four customers with a gender and an age.
We have our item table: five
items, a category of the
item, just t-shirts and jackets,
just in blue and red, and
finally we have our stores.
And we have six stores that
are in various cities in Santa
Clara, San Mateo County in
California and King County in Washington.
Our first query is simply the complete star join.
So, we&#39;re joining all four tables
using the foreign key references
in the fact table, to the keys in the dimension tables.
Now since these are foreign key
references, you can think of
this star join as simply
extending the tuples in the
sales table with further information
about the store item and customer
mentioned in each one.
So, here we go.
And we should expect again sixty tuples in the results,
one for each tuple in the
fact table, and we can
see that we have the information from
the fact table, but then
we also have more information that
we&#39;ve joined in from the dimension tables.
Now it&#39;s not typical to do
the complete star join, usually
we would have at least constrained the star join in some way.
So, our next query will do
selections and projections on the star JOIN.
We&#39;re going to limit ourselves to
sales where the state of the
sale is California, the category
is t-shirt, the age of
the customer is less than 22,
and the last condition is actually over the fact table,
saying the price of the purchase was less than 25.
And now we&#39;ll return
the city, color, customer name, and price of the item.
We run the query and we
see now that we have
just 5 sales that meet our criteria.
So, we&#39;ve seen the star JOIN
with constraints on the
star JOIN, but what&#39;s even more
common in OLAP applications, is
to do grouping and aggregation in order to analyze the data.
And we&#39;re going to start by
looking at grouping it in
the aggregation involving the dimension
attributes in the group
by, and then the
dependent attribute being aggregated.
This is a very common form of query.
So here we&#39;ll say we want
to analyze our data based on
combinations of stores and customers.
So, we&#39;ll group by store ID and customer ID.
And then, we&#39;ll sum up
to see the total sales for
each combination of store and customer.
So, here&#39;s our result.
Now, maybe not that meaningful
to us right now, just
looking at the store IDs and
customer IDs, but for an analyst, it might be meaningful.
We&#39;ll see in a moment doing
group by an aggregation on other
attributes that look a little more interesting.
So now I&#39;ll demonstrate the concept of drilling down.
So you might remember drilling down
says that we&#39;re looking at data
that&#39;s aggregated in some fashion,
and we decide we want more detail.
We get more detail by adding
more attributes to the
group by, so, let&#39;s say in
this case I want to break
out, not only by store and
customer, but also by item.
So, I&#39;ll add item ID to
the group by, and also to
the select, and when I
run this query, I see
that I get more results, and
I now have more detail
in the analysis of the data.
Now I don&#39;t have 60 tuples
in my result even though I&#39;m
grouping by all three dimension
attributes, because I do
have in my fact table
more than one tuple for some
combinations of store, item, and customer.
Next, I&#39;m gonna introduce a query that shows the concept called slicing.
Slicing of course evokes the data cube.
We&#39;ve talked about the data cube
in the previous video, and we
specifically used this example to
demonstrate a three-dimensional data cube.
So, the idea of a
slicing query is a query
that analyzes a slice of
the cube and it does
that by constraining one of the dimensions.
So what I am going to
do, is add to this query
a constraint that says
let&#39;s only consider sales that are from the state of Washington.
And when I add that we&#39;ll
continue to do the group
by an aggregation, but only on
that slice of the cube
representing Washington stores, the sales that are from Washington stores.
So it made a few changes to the query.
The first thing we see is
that I added the store
relation to the from clause
in order to constrain the
state of the sale, I
have to join with the store
table that dimension table so that
I can access
the value of state which is not present in the sales table.
So I also had to add
variables, and I add
the join condition for the
sales table to join
with the dimension table, and then I add the constraint
that the state is Washington.
The last small change is to
add a variable to the
store ID, so that I don&#39;t get an ambiguous error.
So now let&#39;s go ahead and
run the query and we see
that we do get a subset of what we had before.
And that subset is the slice
of the data cube, if you
want to think of it that way,
representing the sales in Washington State.
Now in addition to slicing, there
is also a notion of dicing,
and again if you imagine the
data cube, what a dice
does is slice in two
dimensions and it gives you a chunk of the cube.
So I am going to add a
condition on the item being sold.
I am going to add that the item must be red.
So then I&#39;m going to be looking
at the chunk of the data
cube that identifies red
items purchased in the state of Washington.
So here&#39;s the query; I&#39;ve added
a third relation to the &quot;from&quot; clause.
I added the item dimension tables
so that I can constrain the color to be red.
I have added a &quot;join&quot; condition, joining
the fact table to the item dimension table.
I have added the condition that the color is red.
And finally, I had to add
again the variable names to
make sure I didn&#39;t get ambiguous attribute references.
So we&#39;ll run this query.
And we see that we get an even smaller portion of the data cube.
Again a dice where we have constrained two dimensions.
So we have seen drilling down and
slicing and dicing, now let&#39;s take a look at rolling up.
Rolling up says that we&#39;re
looking at our data
analysis, and we decide that it&#39;s too detailed.
We want to have less detail, in other words, more aggregation.
To do that, we take attributes out of the group by clause.
So let&#39;s say this is way,
way too much detail and we
just want our sales broken down on item.
So we take all of
the attributes out of our
group by clause except for item.
Here we go.
And then, when we run the
query, we&#39;ll see much more summarized data.
And here it is, broken down again, just by separate items.
So far, our grouping and
aggregation has been on
the dimension attributes, specifically the
ID attributes identifying the tuples in the dimension table.
And that may be meaningful for
analyses, but for this
demonstration, it&#39;s more fun
to look at attributes that actually
mean something to us.
So, let&#39;s try a few
queries that group instead based
on attributes in the dimension tables.
We&#39;ll still be using the fact table.
We&#39;ll be joining it with dimension tables.
And here we&#39;re going to start by
grouping on the state and the category of the sales.
Again, summing up the total
sales for the different groups.
So, here we see that
we have four combinations of
state and category California or
Washington jackets and t-shirts,
and then we have the total
sales in each of those
so we can see in both states
the sales for jackets account
for considerably more than the
sales for t-shirts, but we
do also notice that in
California there&#39;s a lot
more sales of t-shirts than
there are in Washington, and I
guess that&#39;s not surprising given the weather.
Now let&#39;s demonstrate drill down on this query.
So let&#39;s say we want a little more information.
Maybe we want a breakdown by county in addition to state.
So to do that, we add
county to the group by
clause and the select
clause, and when we
run the query we see we do now have more detail.
We can see, for example, that
we had more jacket sales in
Santa Clara County than in
San Mateo County although the
t-shirts were approximately equal.
A little, actually, more t-shirts in San Mateo.
This is a little surprising, because
Santa Clara is generally warmer than
San Mateo, but it&#39;s fabricated data.
Now let&#39;s see, we want it
drilled it down even further, and
we want to break our
data down by gender as well as the other attributes.
In order to drill down based
on gender, I first needed
to add the customer table to our from clause.
Prior to this, we weren&#39;t
doing any analysis that involved
any attributes of the customer table.
And so I need to add the join condition here.
And then to do the drill
down, I add the gender attribute
to the group by and to the select.
We run the query, and what do we find?
Well, we can see, for
example that not too many
females in San Mateo County
are buying t-shirts. Most of those
t-shirt sales are counted for by males.
The other thing we notice
is that we don&#39;t have every
single combination of county, category and gender.
Very specifically we look and
we can see that no males
in King County bought any t-shirts.
So we only have in our
result, those combinations of dimension
values that actually appear in the fact table.
Or in the join of the fact table with the dimension tables.
Now let&#39;s suppose after I&#39;ve
gotten to this level of
analysis, I&#39;ve decided that what
might be most interesting is the
data broken down just by combination of state and gender.
So that would be a roll-up operation.
And remember for roll-up I
take attributes out of the group by clause.
So I take out the county
and category and I&#39;m just interested in state/gender combinations.
By the way at this point if
I wanted to, I could remove
the item table because I&#39;m
no longer constraining based on
items or grouping based on items.
But I&#39;ll just leave it in for now, it&#39;s not going to make a difference in our result.
Of course for efficiency I might just prefer to take it out.
Anyway let&#39;s run the query
and now we see that rolled up data.
And when we look at
it I guess our main conclusion here
would be that in our database,
the Californian males are the big spenders.
So far everything we&#39;ve seen
has actually just used the
regular SQL constructs that we already knew about.
Although we were demonstrating them over
a star schema and we&#39;re
showing the types of queries that
one tends to run over star
schema&#39;s in OLAP applications.
Now we&#39;re going to move to
the specific constructs that have
been added to SQL for OLAP.
As you may remember the two
constructs are called With Cube
and With Rollup and they are written in the group by-clause.
So our first query is the
absolute basic cube query.
We start with our sales
fact table, we group on
all three of its dimensions,
and then we add With Cube.
And what we&#39;re going to get
is, basically, the data
in the data cube that we
saw in our previous video that introduced the cube.
Let&#39;s go ahead and run the query.
Disappointingly we get an
error message that this version
of MySQL doesn&#39;t yet support cube.
Actually no version of MySQL
supports cube at this
point in time but we&#39;re hopeful that a future one will.
In fact of the three
open source systems that we
have been using for our demos only
MySQL supports the with
rollup so we will continue
with MySQL and in fact
you can get the same result
that you would get if with
cube was supported, using with roll
up, although it&#39;s a little bit
contorted, but I&#39;ll do that
now, to demonstrate what you would get if you wrote with cube.
So here&#39;s the query, I&#39;m not
going to explain it, if you&#39;re
particularly interested in it, you
can download our script and exam it yourself.
Again what I&#39;m most interested in
is looking at the results, and here they are.
So this result is the
result of a With Cube
on the grouping and aggregation
on all dimensions of our sales table, all three dimensions.
So some of our tuples look very normal.
This first tuple, second, and
third tuple are all giving
us the total price for combination
of store, item, and customer,
and these are exactly what we
got in our original query that
didn&#39;t have the With-Cube operator.
But now we see some
tuples that have blanks and as
a reminder, blanks in this interface mean null.
So this tuple is store item and null.
And what this corresponds to is
an element on the face of the cube.
So this is the face of the
cube that&#39;s not constraining the customer dimension.
And what the value gives us
then is the value we
have on the face of the
cube, which is the
total sales for the
combination of store one
and item one and any customer, and that&#39;s seventy.
And we can cross check that
by seeing that the first
three tuples add up to
70, because those happen to be
the three customers that have made
purchases at Store 1 and Item 1.
And we can similarly see
for Store 1 and Item
2 the total sales are 150.
If we scroll down
a bit we&#39;ll see cases where
we have other single-null values;
I&#39;ll keep going until I find one here.
For example, here we have
the null value for the
store and that would
be the face of the cube
that&#39;s not constraining the store dimension.
So that would be the sum
for Item 1 and Customer
1 at any store, Item 1 and Customer 2 to at any store.
Then we also have tuples that have two null values, here&#39;s an example.
So this one is going to be corresponding to the edge of the cube.
so this is the edge of
the cube that is along
the store dimension and is
picking out Store 5 along
that dimension and then giving
the total sales for all
items and all customers in
Store 5, and we see that.
And again we&#39;ll see other
instances where we&#39;re missing
two values, scroll down to get here.
We&#39;ve got one where we&#39;re
missing the store in the
item, so this would be
on the edge along the customer dimension.
So this gives us the total
sales for any store item made by customer 3.
And then finally, if we
find it, we&#39;ll find the
one that&#39;s all three null values,
and that&#39;s right here.
So that represents the corner of the cube.
That gives us the total
for all stores, all items and all customers.
So, what we&#39;ve done
here by adding With Cube--and again,
that would be the result if
this query here were supported--what
we&#39;re getting is the contents
of the data cube, which are the
inner parts of the cube,
which is what we would get without
adding anything to our group
by and what we saw in one
of our very first queries of
the demo, in addition to the
data on the faces, the
edges, and the corner of the cube.
Now let&#39;s do a quick cross check.
So this data tells us
that the corner of the cube,
here, the one with all null
values, is 33.50 total price.
So, that should be exactly what we
get if we sum up
our prices without doing any
grouping or aggregation so lets give that a try.
So we merely take our sales
table, we sum up the
total prices and we run
it and indeed we get thirty-three fifty.
So now we&#39;ve seen how SQL
can be used to effectively create the data cube.
Sometimes in OLAP applications it&#39;s convenient to query the cube directly.
So people frequently create data
cube say, in SQL using
a materialized view, or just
by creating a table that contains
the result of the data cube which is what we are going to do.
There are even some systems that
use the data cube as their basic native data model.
So let&#39;s go ahead and take
the result of our cube
query and put it in a table.
So I&#39;ve just added &quot;create
table cube as&quot; before our
query and the one the
other thing I did was add a
name to the result of
the aggregation attribute so
that we can refer to it in the data cube.
So P then will then be
containing the sum of the price for
the items inside the data
cube as well as for the faces, edges, and corners.
So, let&#39;s go ahead and create
that table and now let&#39;s look at querying the cube directly.
So, the first thing you will notice in
the next few queries is that
we&#39;ve replaced the sales table
with the cube table so we&#39;re
gonna run our queries directly on the
cube and we can
join the cube with the
store and item tables and
the customer, if we needed it,
just as we joined the sales
table because it does contain the same dimension attributes.
What the cube gives us is
pre-aggregated data, both for
the store, a customer and item combinations.
As well as the data
that has null values that is
already aggregated for the
faces edges and corner of the cube as we&#39;ll just see in a moment.
So what our query is going
to do is find total
sales of blue items in the state of California.
And it will start by showing the
tupples that are used to get that total.
So we&#39;ll join our cube table
with the store and the item
dimension tables in order to
constrain the state and the
color and then we will constrain the state and the color.
Notice the last thing we
say is that customer ID
is null and that&#39;s going
to give us the data on the
face of the cube that
doesn&#39;t go along with the customer&#39;s dimension.
That means it&#39;s going to
be pre-aggregated for all customers
and that&#39;s what we want since
we don&#39;t care about the customers
and just about the color and the state.
So, let&#39;s first run this query
and we see we get six tuples,
and these tuples are all
from the portion of the result
of that cube query we ran
that has a null value for
customer ID and that
is all combinations of stores of
items, and if we checked
our dimension tables we&#39;d see
that these stores are in California
and these items are blue and
these are our total sales broken
down by store and item.
Finally, to get the total total sales,
we&#39;ll just sum up our column
&quot;p&quot; which remember was
the sum of price in the data queue.
So we replace C dot star with sum
of p and we run
the query and we see that our total is 13.65.
Now let me show you something that
may seem non-intuitive at first,
but if you think about it
or maybe run the queries yourself,
you&#39;ll start to understand exactly what&#39;s happening.
I&#39;m going to go back to c. in the select clause.
And incidentally, I didn&#39;t mention
it before but C dot star gives us
in the select clause all the
attributes from the cube
table, and that is
showing which tuples are being used for the aggregation.
So, we had before six tuples that were being used.
Now, I&#39;m going to make one tiny change to the query.
Instead of finding the customer
IDs that are null, I&#39;m going
to find the customer IDs that are not null.
I&#39;m going to run that query, and
I see that we have fourteen tuples now.
What we&#39;ve actually done is moved
away from the face of
the cube and into the cube,
and I&#39;ve said don&#39;t give me
any of the summarized data, just
give me the original values that
are the store item and customer together.
So, I&#39;ve taken away the summaries,
but actually this should still give me the same answer.
Let&#39;s make sure that&#39;s the case.
I do sum of P, and
I run it, and I get $13.65.
So, what happened here is I
used what&#39;s effectively the same
data, but broken down by customer.
And I added it up, that
was a less efficient query, but
both of those queries do
give the correct result, they do
give you the total sales of California
stores&#39; blue items.
Again, I encourage you to
download these and run them
yourself to figure out exactly what&#39;s
going on.
And as a last demonstration of
this very same query, we
can actually go back to the sales table.
Let&#39;s say we don&#39;t even have our data cube.
So, we&#39;re gonna use our sales table
instead, and it should
give us the same result, but
even less efficient than the the last query that we did.
So, you can see here I&#39;ve
changed the cube to be
the sales and all the C dots to F dots.
I took away the constraints
on being null or not null,
since that&#39;s not relevant in the sales table.
Otherwise, the query looks pretty much the same.
So, let&#39;s run this much
and see how many tuples we are operating on now.
So now, we&#39;re operating on 25 tuples.
So, this is the original completely broken down data.
Just as a reminder, in the
data cube, even in the
cells, we&#39;ll be summarizing
or summing for the combination
of store item and customer.
So, if we have three tuples that
are the same store item and customer,
those will be broken out in
the sales table and summarized in
the cube, even in the
least summarized portion of the cube, if you get what I&#39;m saying.
So now, we&#39;ve got our 25
tuples, and if we
sum up the price of those
twenty-five tuples, we should
get that same result, &quot;$13.65&quot;, and we do.
So, we saw that we had
six tuples in the
most efficient query over the data cube.
When we used just a center
portion of the cube, we had
fourteen or something, I actually
don&#39;t remember the exact number, and then 25.
All of them gave us the same answer.
Obviously these numbers are very
small, but if you think about
huge data that has millions
or tens of millions of rows,
then we&#39;re talking about dramatic differences
in how much data needs to
be summarized or aggregated in order to get the answer.
So, using the summary data from
the cube can be orders of
magnitude faster than going to the original fact data.
Now a variation on the
with cube is to give
specific attributes with the cube operator itself.
And what that says is to
only give summaries for
these dimension attributes and not the others.
In other words, we&#39;ll only see null
values in the result for the store ID and customer ID
and we won&#39;t see any null values for the Item ID.
So, in some sense, we&#39;re
materializing just some of
the faces, edges, and corner
of the cube, not all of them.
If we run this query, well,
we&#39;ll get the same results that
MySQL doesn&#39;t yet support it,
but this is the SQL standard
for the cube operator with subsets of attributes.
As before, I&#39;ve cooked up an
equivalent query using a MySQL&#39;s
With Rollup command, and I&#39;m
certainly not going to explain it,
but you&#39;re welcome to download it and examine it.
What I really like to look
at is the result, and here it is.
So, this looks a lot like our
original data cube but what we will notice is
that there are no null values
in the item column.
So, it&#39;s a subset of the result of the cube query.
And we would use that when
we know we&#39;re never going to be rolling up on items.
So, that dimension, the summaries
based on that dimension aren&#39;t going to be useful to us.
Now, let&#39;s look at With Rollup,
which is supported natively by the MySQL system.
With Rollup, again, gives us a subset of the data.
cube.
But, it&#39;s a very specific one
and it&#39;s based on the ordering of
the attributes in the group by clause.
So, let me just go ahead and run it and explain what we get.
We again get null values,
and those null values indicate the summary.
For example, the Store 1, Item 1 and 70 is.
The sum of prices for
all customers for Store 1 and Item 1.
And we see Store 1, Item 2, as well.
We again see cases with
two null values, so this
is the summary for Store 1,
all of the items and customers,
the total sales, and we
also have the triple null somewhere.
It&#39;s at the bottom this time, with total sales of $33.50.
But what we&#39;ll see
is that we don&#39;t have all combinations of null values.
We have a null value for customer
ID, or we have nulls
for the combination of customer ID
and item ID, or all three nulls.
So we only have the right-hand
attribute or the two
most-right attributes or all
of them and if we had
a fourth dimension, we&#39;d see that
we have the right-most, two right-most, three right-most.
This doesn&#39;t really make any
particular sense for this query,
but it&#39;s used when we have dimensions that are hierarchical.
And I actually introduced a hierarchical
dimensions in our original schema just for this purpose.
So, lets turn to that query.
So, here&#39;s a query that&#39;s grouping
by the state, county, and city.
These are three dimension attributes,
they all come from the store dimension table.
And they are hierarchical, meaning
that we don&#39;t have every
combination of state, county and city.
We have cities that are in
specific counties, and counties
that are in specific states.
So, when we look at the results
of the query, we see, of
course, that we, when we
have San Mateo is always in the state of California.
King County is always in the state of Washington.
We don&#39;t have Palo Alto combined
with, say, King County with state California.
So, we don&#39;t have all the combinations of the three.
We have a hierarchical structure on them.
And it&#39;s this structure that makes sense when we use a roll-up.
So, let&#39;s add With Rollup to this query and see what we get.
So, here in our result we see
our original tuples for a state, county, city combination.
And then, we see for example,
this tuple here, which is
taking the state of California
and the county of San Mateo
and adding up all of the sales there.
And we see similarly that we have all of the sales for Santa Clara County.
Then we can see that we
have all of the sales for
each state, so this is
the California sales and the Washington sales.
And finally, the triple null is
the corner of the cube, it&#39;s
all of our sales and, as
usual, we get the total of $33.50.
Now, what don&#39;t we
see in here compared with the data cube?
Well, we don&#39;t see, for example,
a tuple that has
California and Palo Alto
and the county as null.
Why is that?
Well, Palo Alto is always in Santa Clara County.
So rolling up the county,
or saying I want California and
Palo Alto sales for every
county, is exactly the
same as saying I want
California and Palo Alto sales in Santa Clara County.
We also don&#39;t see, for
example, the state and county both being null.
For example, if we had
Seattle as a city and
the state and county being null.
Well, Seattle is always in
King County and always in
Washington, so we&#39;re not aggregating
anything there, we get the
exact same results as having Seattle King in Washington.
So if we ran WITH CUBE
on this hierarchically-structured data, we&#39;d
actually not get anymore information,
we&#39;d have a bigger result, but it wouldn&#39;t be giving us more information.
It would just be less efficient for getting the same data.
So that concludes our OLAP demonstration.
We saw Star Schema and
we saw plain SQL queries over that schema.
We saw the concept of drilling
down and rolling up; also slicing and dicing.
We introduced a WITH CUBE
extension to SQL, which is
not yet implemented in MySQL,
but we were able to write
a query that&#39;s equivalent to WITH CUBE.
We also saw putting a WITH
CUBE query into a table
and then querying that table directly
and that can be much more efficient
than running the equivalent query
in SQL directly over the fact table.
We also saw WITH ROLLUP, which is implemented.
We didn&#39;t demonstrate putting the
result of WITH ROLLUP in a table, but we could certainly do that too.
All of these features are useful
primarily in applications that
are performing analyses over very
large data sets that exhibit
this dimensional type structure, but
this is actually quite a
common structure in analysis applications.